<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A new declaration from eight regiments in the Army, viz. The Generals Life-Guard, Lieutenant Gen. Cromwels Regiment. Commissary Gen. Iretons Regiment. Col. Rainsboroughs Reg. Collonel Whaleyes Regiment. Colonell Bark[s]teeds Regiment. Colonell Overttons Regiment. And Colonell Hewsons Regiment. Presented, to his Excellency Sir Thomas Fairfax neere Kingston, at his advance towards Windsor; concerning their loyalty to his Majesty, their due respect to his Excellency, and their desires touching the publique weale of the Kingdome. Also the copy of a letter from the Army, discovering a further conspiracie against the Parliament, Army, and Kingdome, neer Mile-Inne, London. With divers particulars touching the same. Imprimatur, Gilb. Mabbott.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1647</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 7 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 5 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A89956</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing N607</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E416_35</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R204513</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99864000</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99864000</idno>
            <idno type="VID">116218</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A89956)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 116218)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 66:E416[35])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A new declaration from eight regiments in the Army, viz. The Generals Life-Guard, Lieutenant Gen. Cromwels Regiment. Commissary Gen. Iretons Regiment. Col. Rainsboroughs Reg. Collonel Whaleyes Regiment. Colonell Bark[s]teeds Regiment. Colonell Overttons Regiment. And Colonell Hewsons Regiment. Presented, to his Excellency Sir Thomas Fairfax neere Kingston, at his advance towards Windsor; concerning their loyalty to his Majesty, their due respect to his Excellency, and their desires touching the publique weale of the Kingdome. Also the copy of a letter from the Army, discovering a further conspiracie against the Parliament, Army, and Kingdome, neer Mile-Inne, London. With divers particulars touching the same. Imprimatur, Gilb. Mabbott.</title>
                  <author>Fairfax, Thomas Fairfax, Baron, 1612-1671.</author>
                  <author>England and Wales. Army.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 6 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by J.C. for G. Horton, and are to be sold in the Old Bayley, and neere the Royall Exchange in Cornhill,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1647.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Imperfect: significant bleed-through.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "Nou: 25".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>England and Wales. --  Army --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Conspiracies --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Civil War, 1642-1649 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-05</date>
            <label>Sarah Wingo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-05</date>
            <label>Sarah Wingo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:116218:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A NEW DECLARATION FROM Eight Regiments in the ARMY, <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <list>
               <item>
                  <hi>The Generals Life-Guard,</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Lieutenant Gen. Cromwels Regiment.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Commiſſary Gen. Iretons Regiment.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Col. Rainſboroughs Reg.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Collonel Whaleyes Regiment.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Colonell Bark <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>eeds Regiment.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Colonell Overttons Regiment.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>AND Colonell Hewſons Regiment.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>PRESENTED, To his Excellency Sir THOMAS FAIRFAX neere <hi>Kingſton,</hi> at his advance towards <hi>Windſor;</hi> Concerning their loyalty to his Majeſty, their due reſpect to his Excellency, and their Deſires touching the Publique Weale of the Kingdome.</p>
            <p>Alſo the Copy of a Letter from the Army, diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vering a further Conſpiraci<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> againſt the Parliament, Army, and Kingdome, neer Mile-Inne, <hi>London.</hi> With divers particulars touching the ſame.</p>
            <floatingText type="license" xml:lang="eng" subtype="imprimatur">
               <body>
                  <p>Imprimatur,</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>GILB. MABBOTT.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>J. C.</hi> for <hi>G. Horton,</hi> and are to be ſold in the Old Bayley, and neere the Royall Exchange in <hi>Cornhill,</hi> 1647.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb facs="tcp:116218:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:116218:2"/>
            <head>The Copy of a Letter from the Army, touching a further diſcovery of the late Plot and Engagement, both a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt King, Parliament, Army and Kingdome.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Worthy Sir,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>SInce the withdrawing of the Army from the la<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> Randezvouz <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ear Ware, the Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall, and the Councell of the Army hath taken into conſideration the intollerable Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion of the Counties adjacent, and the great burthen which they have a long time under go<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e, and after ſome reſult thereupon, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved to withdrew the Army at a further di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance from your City, leaving onely one Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giment of Foot <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> to quarter with you for the better levying of the arreares ſo long
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:116218:3"/>due to the army, which Regiment (I am con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fident) will deport themſelves with ſo much civility, that you will have no occaſion to mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mure at their reſidence with you. Yet (I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe) it may prove very prejudiciall, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructive to the proceedings of the obnoxious Party, who have ſought both Army and King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes ruine, and endeavoured to beget diviſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on among the Souldiery, and diſ-unite this u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>imous Army, &amp;c. as appeareth by their late actions at ſeverall meetings within the city, but eſpecially at the Grand Councell held neare Mile-Inne, adjoyning to your city, where a great number of the chiefe Head-pieces did re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſort, as it is credibly reported by a friend of ours, who were ſometimes converſant with them for the better accompliſhing of their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſignes, and withdrawing others from their for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mor obedience, till at the laſt they were diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered, their councels and debates fruſtrated, and the chiefe Actors (both in City and Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my) ſecured.</p>
            <p>For their conſultations did tend much to diviſion and diſcord, and very deſtructive to Government, and had got neare upon twenty
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:116218:3"/>thouſand Weavers (under pretence of redreſs) to appeare at the late Rande<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>vouze, had not their deſign been moſt happily and timely pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vented.</p>
            <p>And it is further advertized, that divers e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minent perſons within the Tower of London were very active in the ſaid Engagement, which will in time appear vifible, and a further diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very be made thereof.</p>
            <p>Wee have alſo received the copy of a Paper diſpierſed upon and down the city, for the ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thering together of the ſaid Weavers, their place of meeting being Mile-Inne Green, and from thence to advance to the randezvouze, to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent a Petition (as it is ſaid) to the Generall, for redreſſe of Grievances, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>The common Souldiery are much incenſed againſt the Adjutators, and are reſolved to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply no longer with them, by reaſon of the great expence they are now at, as alſo the many ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructions that doth now ariſe, through out di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers regiments in the army occaſioned by the ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>id party, inſomuch, that they are now like to practiſe their formerpoſtures, and bee no more our Maſte<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>.</p>
            <pb n="4" facs="tcp:116218:4"/>
            <p>Divers Regiments in the Army have decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red their ardent affection to the Generall, upon his Excellencies advance towards Winſor, viz. the Generals Life Guard, Lieutenant Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall Cromwels Regiment, Commiſſary Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall Iretons Regiment, Col. Whaleyes, colonell Rainsboroughs, colonell Barkſteeds, colonell Overtons, and colonell Hewſons Regiments; the ſubſtance of which Declaration followes in theſe words:</p>
            <p>
               <hi>THat whereas there hath many divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions lately aroſe and ſprung up in the body of the Army, occaſioned by the late diſtractions, therefore they humbly deſire, that all diſcontents might be removed, the Souldiers not put to ſhifts, or the Countrey ſo grievouſly oppreſſed, declaring, That if not timely prevented and remedied, will doubtleſſe render this Army which God hath often honoured with rema<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>k able teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies of his preſence, under the proſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous conduct of your Excellency, no better
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:116218:4"/>then an hend leſſe and confuſed multitude; wherefore ſenſibly apprehending the wofull effect of diſ-unity and diſorder, we preſume it abſolutely neceſſary <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ut of our duty to God moſt obedient loyalty to his Maieſtie, due reſpct to your Excellencie, and tender re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard to the weale both of Army and King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, to improve our utmuſt endeavours to prevent the miſer able conſequences, which inevitably enſue Diviſu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> and the mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strous confuſion which unavoidably attends diſorder,</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Therefore, we do hereby eertifie and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare, that we acknowledge <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> ſel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>es obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged to ſub<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ilt unto your Excellencies Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands; Withall profeſſing, that our hearts deſires to preſerve the band of unity, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all intentions to continue our accuſtomed o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience,</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="6" facs="tcp:116218:5"/>
            <p>All which they preſented to the Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral, at the laſt Randezvouz of the Army <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>eer <hi>Kingſton.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus have I imparted unto you, that which (for preſent) is moſt conſiderable, onely this, that ſome Agents in the late Deſigne have fell from their diſſenting party, and are very ſubmiſſive and obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dient to the Generals Orders, which that they may all doe, is the deſire of</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>Windſor,</hi> 
                  <date>Novem. 22. 1647.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your faithfull ſervart,</hi> Robert Hall.</signed>
            </closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
